Register of the Firing Line (Television Program) broadcast records 80040.4089238
Hoover Institution Archives
Firing Line (Television program) broadcast records
1966-1999
Hoover Institution Archives
Buckley, William F., Jr., 1925-2008.
Southern Educational Communications Association
80040.4089238
948.1 linear feet 189 manuscript boxes, 218 oversize boxes, 3 card file boxes, 1 motion picture film, 352 linear feet of videotapes
The Firing Line broadcast records include videotapes from the Firing Line television show, as well as sound recordings, administrative and speaker files, program research files, photographs, transcripts, and other materials from the show. The types of program research materials available for each program are listed in the Episode Guide. The Episode Guide also includes a summary and guest list for each episode, as well as a link to the episode details page on Hoover's digital collections website. When applicable, links for purchasing full-length episodes and the availability of special order DVDs are also included. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Access
Collection is open for research. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Use copies of some videos in this collection are available for immediate access. To listen to sound recordings or to view other videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1980, with a large increment acquired in 2001.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Historical Note
With 1,505 installments over 33 years, Firing Line is the longest-running public-affairs show with a single host, William F. Buckley Jr., in television history.
Firing Line kept substantially the same basic format throughout its run, but with certain variations.
(1) It began as an hour-long show for commercial television (i.e., with time subtracted for commercial breaks), syndicated by WOR in New York City.
In 1971, under the auspices of the Southern Educational Communications Association (SECA), it moved to public television and became a full hour. This move is reflected in a numbering change in the programs: shows numbered 1 through 240 were on commercial television; the SECA series then begins with s0001, taped on May 26, 1971. The WOR shows were numbered according to the order in which they were taped; the SECA shows were numbered according to the order in which they were first broadcast.
In 1988 the length of the regular shows was changed to a half-hour.
(2) Starting in 1978, interspersed among the regular shows are occasional specials and two-hour formal debates, with opening statements, cross-examination, and closing statements. The debates were initially numbered as regular shows (the first Firing Line Debate was s0306, although a debate sponsored by Columbia College's Debate Council was filmed as shows s0296 and s0297 a few weeks earlier). Beginning in 1986, a separate numbering system was instituted for Firing Line Specials (with the number prefaced by the letters FLS). (Note: Debates listed as "Part I" and "Part II" were shown on consecutive weeks in the regular time slot, rather than being shown all at once in a special two-hour time slot.)
Starting with S0961 in March of 1993, the formal debate would often be followed by two or more shows in which roughly the same participants were released from the debate format for informal discussion.
(3) Over the years, Buckley and his producer, Warren Steibel, used various methods of bringing an extra perspective to the discussion. In the early years there would often be a panel of three questioners--sometimes students, sometimes adults.
Starting in 1977 there would often be a single "examiner," who would play a larger part in the proceedings than the panel of questioners had typically done. The examiners who appeared most frequently were Jeff Greenfield, Michael Kinsley, Harriet Pilpel, and Mark Green.
In 1988, when the show went to half an hour, the examiner was eliminated, but there was often a "moderator," whose role was similar to that of the moderator in a formal debate. The moderator would introduce both host and guest, and then ask the opening question. The moderator appearing most frequently was Michael Kinsley. Some early programs included a person called a "chairman," who functioned like a moderator.
(4) Beginning with show 171, in October of 1969, approximately twice a year the tables would be turned, with a panel of questioners putting Buckley "on the firing line."
Source: Preface to the program catalogue compiled by Firing Line staff member Linda Bridges, included in box 1.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection contains the records of the Firing Line television series, which was hosted by William F. Buckley Jr. Materials include the original broadcast videotapes from Firing Line, as well as transcripts, photographs, sound recordings, program research materials, and other materials. The types of materials available for each program vary.
The collection is organized into three series: Episode Guide, Production Materials File, and Audiovisual File.
The Episode Guide is arranged by show number and includes the title, episode summary, and guest names for each show. Numbers that are followed by an "R" are repeat broadcasts of the same program, while numbers followed by an "E" are edited repeat broadcasts. When applicable, links for purchasing full-length episodes and the availability of special order DVDs are also included. The Episode Guide also lists the supporting documentation for each program: background files, publicity files, and transcripts. Supporting documentation varies by program.
Background files include program research materials such as clippings, correspondence, transcripts, histories, press summaries, and printed matter, as well as collected materials on speakers and their appearances on Firing Line.
Publicity files are available for public television shows produced by SECA and contain materials such as photographs, negatives, slides, transcripts, newsletters, and other materials. The types of materials available for each show vary.
Transcripts of Firing Line are both typewritten and printed. Also included among transcripts are two productions hosted by William F. Buckley Jr. that were not Firing Line programs. The shows have been designated as 000a and 000b. These programs are included in the Episode Guide and the transcripts are located in box 159. Downloadable transcripts for most Firing Line programs are available on Hoover's digital collections website and can be accessed through the links that accompany each program entry in the Episode Guide.
The Production Materials File includes administrative files and speaker and research files. Administrative files document the creation of the program. Files contain a catalogue of transcripts; Firing Line guests' topic lists; programs lists; special debates lists; correspondence with prominent politicians, economists, and scientists; and viewer comments and suggestions. Press releases, newsletters, newspaper clippings, and files on William F. Buckley Jr. and Warren Steibel, Firing Line's producer-director, are also included. Photographs, negatives, and slides of William F. Buckley Jr. individually and with the guests on his shows complete the records.
Speaker and research files include clippings, correspondence, transcripts, histories, press summaries, and printed matter, as well as other collected materials on speakers and their appearances on Firing Line. Not every show or speaker is represented with a file. The original order of the files was retained, and they are arranged alphabetically by the last name of the speaker. Speakers who made multiple appearances may have several files. The William F. Buckley Jr. book On the Firing Line: The Public Life of Our Public Figures (Random House, New York, 1989) contains an alphabetical list of guests who appeared on Firing Line (see box 7).
The Audiovisual File includes videorecordings, sound recordings, and motion picture film.
Sound recordings contain sound tracks of the early Firing Line television shows on open reel tapes and compact sound cassettes.
Videorecordings include the original broadcast videotapes from Firing Line. Many videotapes have been reformatted to more durable media; additional reformatting depends on funding. Priority for reformatting is assigned to the most endangered videotapes and those programs in highest demand from viewers. Reformatted programs can be viewed on Hoover's digital collections website or on-site in the reading room, or purchased from Amazon. videotapes of programs that have not been reformatted cannot be viewed at this time. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives at hoover_visuals@stanford.edu for more information.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Conservatism.; United States--Foreign relations--20th century.; United States--Politics and government--20th century.; Video tapes.; Buckley, William F., Jr., 1925-2008.; Southern Educational Communications Association
- Episode Guide, 1966-1999
  Scope and Contents note
  The Episode Guide is arranged by show number. Numbers that are followed by an "R" are repeat broadcasts of the same program, while numbers followed by an "E" are edited repeat broadcasts. Guests are listed with the program title, using Library of Congress name authorities, in a last name, first name sequence.
  When applicable, links for purchasing full-length episodes and the availability of special order DVDs are also included. The Episode Guide also includes links to Hoover's digital collections website for each program and information about the three types of program research materials: background files, publicity files, and transcripts.
  Background files include materials such as clippings, correspondence, transcripts, histories, press summaries, and printed matter, as well as other collected materials on speakers and their appearances on Firing Line.
  Publicity files are available for public television shows produced by SECA and contain materials such as photographs, negatives, slides, transcripts, newsletters, and other materials, The types of materials available for each show vary.
  Transcripts of Firing Line are both typewritten and printed. Also included among transcripts are two productions hosted by William F. Buckley Jr. that were not Firing Line programs. The shows have been designated as 000a and 000b. These programs are included in the Episode Guide, and the transcripts are located in box 159. Downloadable transcripts for most Firing Line programs are available on Hoover's digital collections website and can be accessed through the links that accompany each program entry in the Episode Guide.
  - "Poverty: Hopeful or Hopeless?" Guests: Harrington, Michael, 1928-, 4 April 1966 (Item Program Number 1)
    Background File: Box/Folder 70: 1
    Transcript: Box/Folder 159: 4
    Program details: President Johnson had just declared war on poverty, and Mr. Harrington, an avowed socialist who had started out on the staff of Dorothy Day's Catholic Worker, had been among the first to enlist. On this show (the first Firing Line taped, though not the first aired), Mr. Harrington begins by describing the despair and consequent lack of initiative engendered by poverty; WFB engages him on the issue of whether we can hope to alleviate either material or emotional poverty through government action. MH: "Being kicked around and being pushed down, living in dense, miserable housing, and dealing with cockroaches and rats are not the kinds of things that make one a balanced, content, normal, and adjusted healthy personality." WFB: "I couldn't agree with you more. But I'm trying to raise the following question: To what extent... can we count on [a poverty program] to alleviate all these concomitant miseries?"
    Availability: On amazon.com. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.1
    DVD Link: http://www.amazon.com/dp/B001MBTSD6
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/5935
  - "Prayer in the Public Schools" Guests: Pike, James A. (James Albert), 1913-1969., 6 April 1966 (Item Program Number 2)
    Background File: Box/Folder 70: 2
    Transcript: Box/Folder 159: 5
    Program details: Bishop Pike was thought of as the wild man of the Episcopal Church (by this time he had been put on trial for heresy, though he had emerged still wearing the Episcopal purple), but on this show he is genial and persuasive on the subject of school prayer specifically and the First Amendment generally. JAP: "I think [the Supreme Court Justices] use the First Amendment in a way it was never intended to be used. [The Founding Fathers] talked about establishment of religion. And they meant, really, establishment like the Church of England is. ... It was forbidding the federal agency, the Congress, from interfering with the existing states' establishment." ... "I personally do not see the value of state-prescribed prayer or of the reading of the Bible, for instance, without study of the background, the context, the thoughtful criticism of the passages, in school. And I think it's a disservice to the Church, too, because it gives parents the illusion that this side of life is being covered by the public agency when, in fact, it's very trivial and perfunctory."
    Availability: On amazon.com. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.2
    DVD Link: http://www.amazon.com/dp/B001N0LEII
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/5936
  - "Vietnam: Pull Out? Stay In? Escalate?" Guests: Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968., 8 April 1966 (Item Program Number 3)
    Background File: Box/Folder 70: 3
    Transcript: Box/Folder 159: 6
    Program details: Mr. Thomas--the grand old man of the American Left, six-time Socialist Party candidate for President--was by this point focusing all his energies on opposition to America's involvement in the Vietnam War. This often fierce exchange, which places both men on the firing line, begins with WFB's asking why his guest supported the Korean War but opposes the Vietnam War and goes on to explore whether it is realistic even to aspire to contain Communism. NT: "Mr. Buckley, you seem to believe in cruelty as a necessary adjunct to this kind of war. Your main point is that somehow we're going to contain Communism this way, and we aren't. We may delay certain events in Communism. We're not going to contain it. We-" WFB: "Excuse me, was the war in Greece cruel? Did we contain the Communists in Greece?"
    Availability: On amazon.com. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.3
    DVD Link: http://www.amazon.com/dp/B001MBTSE0
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/5937
  - "Capital Punishment" Guests: Allen, Steve, 1921-, 11 April 1966 (Item Program Number 4)
    Background File: Box/Folder 70: 4
    Transcript: Box/Folder 159: 7
    Program details: The death penalty was under heavy attack in the courts and in public forums, and polls indicated that it was the issue that most sharply divided liberals from conservatives. Messrs. Buckley and Allen begin by discussing why this should be a touchstone issue, and progress to considerations of whether the death penalty in fact deters, and whether, even if it does, it can be morally defended. SA: I think there are probably various reasons why conservatives generally favor capital punishment. I think one of them maybe so obvious there is the traditional risk of overlooking it, and that is simply that it exists and that it has existed for a long time."
    Availability: On amazon.com. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.4
    DVD Link: http://www.amazon.com/dp/B001MBTSEK
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/5938
  - "Where Does the Civil-Rights Movement Go Now?" Guests: Farmer, James, 1920-, 18 April 1966 (Item Program Number 5)
    Background File: Box/Folder 70: 5
    Transcript: Box/Folder 159: 8
    Program details: "Two years after the Civil Rights Act was passed, Mr. Farmer was arguing for what he called affirmative action," WFB suggests, and Mr. Farmer denies hotly and cogently--though not, as it would turn out, presciently--that affirmative action would almost certainly turn into numerical quotas. One sample: JF: "President Kennedy, incidentally, adopted the same idea. It's said that he stepped off a plane in Washington. There was an honor guard there to meet him. He saw no Negroes. He called an officer, and said, 'I see no Negroes here.' The officer said, 'Mr. President, no Negroes have applied.' He said, 'Go out and find some.'" WFB: "Well, one hopes he will find more productive jobs for Negroes than simply to make them stand parade for dignitaries."
    Availability: Special order, please contact the Archives. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.5
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/5939
  - "Should the House Committee on Un-American Activities Be Abolished?" Guests: Faulk, John Henry., 21 April 1966 (Item Program Number 6)
    Background File: Box/Folder 70: 6
    Transcript: Box/Folder 159: 9
    Program details: "Mr. Faulk is primarily known," WFB begins, "as a certified victim of an anti-Communist organization called Aware," which had brought him to the attention of the House Committee on Un-American Activities. Mr. Faulk had sued Aware and been awarded "the most colossal judgment in libel history"; he was now seeking the abolition of the committee. On this show, Mr. Faulk begins, in his down-home sort of voice, by quoting the then-Grand Dragon of the Ku Klux Klan as having said that "the committee's program so closely parallels the program of the Ku Klux Klan that there is no distinguishable difference between them," and we're off to the races.
    Availability: On amazon.com. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.6
    DVD Link: http://www.amazon.com/dp/B001MBTSF4
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/5940
  - "The Prevailing Bias" Guests: Susskind, David, 1920-, 2 May 1966 (Item Program Number 7)
    Background File: Box/Folder 70: 7
    Transcript: Box/Folder 159: 10
    Program details: The tone is set in the first few minutes, when Mr. Susskind responds to the introduction (in which WFB had said, among other things, "Mr. Susskind is a staunch liberal. If there were a contest for the title Mr. Eleanor Roosevelt, he would unquestionably win it") by saying: "I must say that I regard that introduction as somewhat rude and insulting, Mr. Buckley. I had hoped, on the occasion of your having your own television program, you would abandon your traditional penchant for personal bitchiness and stick to facts and issues; but evidently your rude behavior is congenital and compulsive. And so I forgive you." But among the billingsgate there is serious discussion of the current offerings on the airwaves, the tendency of the Jewish community to resist the anti-Communist movement, and more.
    Availability: On amazon.com. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.7
    DVD Link: http://www.amazon.com/dp/B001E50RQ2
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/5941
  - "The New Frontier: The Great Society" Guests: Goodwin, Richard N., 6 May 1966 (Item Program Number 8)
    Background File: Box/Folder 70: 8
    Transcript: Box/Folder 159: 11
    Program details: Mr. Goodwin was present at the creation--as WFB reminds us, "he is credited with supplying that ominous phrase, 'The Great Society' "--and he defends the Johnson program ably in this good-tempered session. RG: "Well, I think the Great Society ...represents a change or a breaking point from the ideas of the New Deal. I think the essential idea behind the New Deal was that rising prosperity, more equitably distributed among the people, would solve most of the problems of the country.... Now, having succeeded-not completely, but to quite a degree-in that effort ... we find it doesn't solve the major problems, the kinds of problems you talked about in your campaign [for Mayor of New York] ...and that now we have to turn our attention, not only ... to relief of the poor or dispossessed, but to the quality of life of every American ..."
    Availability: On amazon.com. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.8
    DVD Link: http://www.amazon.com/dp/B001MBTSFO
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/5942
  - "Civil Disobedience: How Far Can It Go?" Guests: Gregory, Dick., 16 May 1966 (Item Program Number 9)
    Background File: Box/Folder 70: 9
    Transcript: Box/Folder 159: 12
    Program details: Mr. Gregory had been arrested many times for his civil disobedience, and he had been shot during the Watts riots. As conversation, this show never quite clicks: Mr. Buckley is trying to clarify the line between peaceful protest and civil disobedience, while Mr. Gregory is engaged in blurring it. Still, a fascinating glimpse of the worldview of an inveterate protestor. DG: When these people [the Nuremberg defendants] pleaded that they were only obeying the law ... the world's justices declared that they were guilty and that man has a duty to disobey laws that are contrary to great moral laws. One day we might have another trial, be it in Heaven, be it in Asia--I don't know if we’ll be judged by the Chinese or by the angels--but I want to be able to plead not guilty."
    Availability: Special order, please contact the Archives. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.9
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/5943
  - "McCarthyism: Past, Present, Future" Guests: Cherne, Leo, 1912-, 16 May 1966 (Item Program Number 10)
    Background File: Box/Folder 70: 10
    Transcript: Box/Folder 159: 13
    Program details: Mr. Buckley seeks, with his old friend and adversary Mr. Cherne, to explore, as he puts it, why Joseph McCarthy's oversimplifications were judged to be almost unique and highly damaging ... whereas the contemporary oversimplifications of, say, a Harry Truman, or, before that, of a Franklin Roosevelt, or subsequently of a Lyndon Johnson, are not seen as that offensive." A rich conversation, full of detail. LC: "Well, to suggest, for example, that General Marshall lied about his whereabouts on the morning of Pearl Harbor, and to suggest, as Senator McCarthy did, that in fact he was meeting Maksim Litvinov at the Washington airport when in fact this was not true--this is not oversimplification in the normal language of political discourse."
    Availability: On amazon.com. Hoover Identifier number: 80040.10
    DVD Link: http://www.amazon.com/dp/B001MBTSG8
    Digital Collections Link: http://digitalcollections.hoover.org/objects/5944
  - "Vietnam: What Next?" Guests: Lynd, Staughton., 23 May 1966 (Item Program Number 11)
    Background File: Box/Folder 70: 11
    Transcript: Box/Folder 159: 14